<?xml version="1.0"?>

<sena>
	<updated>July 15, 2013</updated>
	<intro>
		<p>This document contains the standards Laurel uses to evaluate all submissions of names and armory for registration. These are the authoritative standards - other documents may summarize or provide simplified versions, but submissions must meet the criteria as laid out here. However, these Rules are not a step-by-step procedure for devising names or armory. Policies for heralds and for the submissions process are in other documents, such as the Administrative Handbook, available on the Laurel website.</p>
		<p>This document is primarily for Laurel to use when making decisions on whether a name or piece of armory can be registered.  Laurel evaluates each submission to ensure that it is period within the framework that these Rules requires, does not conflict with other registered items, and is not presumptuous or offensive.</p>
		<p>We make these Rules available so that anyone interested can read and learn about the standards. They are also used by the members of the College of Arms in advising Laurel on whether a submission meets these standards.</p>
		<p>We encourage submitters and newer heralds to use the training materials available on the Laurel website. These materials give instructions for creating medieval-style names and armory. They explain the processes for submitting those names and armory for registration. They give overviews of these rules that are sufficient to answer most questions. However, in the case of any differences between the Standards for Evaluation of Names and Armory and the other documents, the Standards for Evaluation of Names and Armory take precedence over other documents.</p>
		<p>These Rules are divided into four main sections, plus appendices. The General Principles section describes some of the fundamental principles that underlie these rules. It also defines some common terms used throughout these rules. The other three main sections each address the standards that each type of submission - personal names, non-personal names, and armory - must meet.  Each main section first lays out the standards for content and style (how submissions must be put together). It then lays out the standards for avoiding conflict (being "too close" to registered items). Finally, it lays out the standards for avoiding presumption (claims that are not allowed) and offense.</p>
		<p>The appendices contain supplemental information that expands on the Rules. One appendix contains the table of languages that can be mixed in a name submission. Other appendices contain information which consolidates decades of Laurel rulings.  These appendices will be updated regularly to keep the material up to date.</p>
	</intro>
	<gp name="Principles of the Standards for Evaluation of Names and Armory">
		<sub name="Governing Documents">
			<p>The Governing Documents of the SCA say that &quot;Laurel shall define standards suitable to the type of item to be registered, and apply them uniformly to all such submissions.  These standards shall be designed to support the historical re-creations of the Society and to provide sufficient difference from names and armory registered within the Society to avoid undue confusion, to avoid the appearance of unearned honors or false claims, and to provide sufficient difference from historical or fictional personages to prevent offense due to obvious usurpation of identity or armory. Members are encouraged to develop unique, historically valid names and armory.&quot;</p>
			<p>These rules define those standards and how submissions can meet them.</p>
		</sub>
		<sub name="These Rules">
			<p>The Standards for Evaluation of Names and Armory are based on the principles expressed in the governing documents, including the following.</p>
			<sub name="Reasonably Period">
				<p>A submission must be reasonably period in nature, to support our historical re-creations.  The rules regarding the standards for what is reasonably period in nature are labeled as &quot;content&quot; and &quot;style&quot; rules.</p>
 <blockquote>
  <p> a. Content rules focus on the elements (words, charges, tinctures) which may be included in a submission.</p>
  <p> b. Style rules focus on how those items may be combined to make a complete submission.  Style rules describe common period patterns and how to document less common patterns.  Submissions demonstrated to be period in style may be registered as individually attested patterns even if they are not explicitly described as registerable in the general style rules.</p>
 </blockquote>
			</sub>
		</sub>
	</gp>
	<gp name="Registration and Documentation">
	</gp>
	<gp name="Definition of Period">
	</gp>
	<gp name="Definitions of Terms Used in these Rules">
	</gp>
</sena>
